Virginia Corwin Papers, 1930-1996
Smith College Archives
Virginia Corwin Papers
1930-1996
Corwin, Virginia
RG 42 UUID:57dfd620-5440-4e7f-902c-0fc9d8e3e42d
4 boxes (2.5 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
The papers of Virginia Corwin contain some papers related to her career at Smith College as Professor of Religion, class notes from her graduate work at Yale University and research notes and preliminary drafts for a book on modern Hinduism.
Virginia Corwin was born in Orange, New Jersey, on August 17, 1901, the daughter of Joseph R. and Caroline (Stallkencht) Corwin. She graduated from Wellesley College in 1923 and received the B.D. from Union Theological Seminary in New York City in 1929; at Union she was a Kent Fellow. In 1930 she came to Smith College as an Instructor of Religion and Biblical Literature. Prof. Corwin entered Yale University in 1932 and received her Ph.D. from it in 1937. Her dissertation was on St. Ignatius, Bishop of Antioch; Yale University Press published a revision of the text in 1960. Prof. Corwin taught at Smith until 1939 when she went to Western Reserve University as Harkness Professor of Biblical Literature and acting head of the Department of Religion. In 1942 Miss Corwin returned to Smith College as an Associate Professor of Religion and was made Professor of Religion in 1953. She retired from Smith College in 1966. After Prof. Corwin retirement she was visiting professor at Claremont College in California and at Wells College in New York.
While at Smith College Prof. Corwin became interested in the study of non-Christian religions and invested time and energy studying Judaism, Islam, Hinduism, Buddhism and other religions. She created courses in these topics and taught them, sometimes in conjunctions her colleague D. Dennis Hudson.
Prof. Corwin was active in the American Academy of Religion and served as its president in 1950. A constant traveler she visited the Asian countries associated with the non-Christian religions.
In 1975 she married Herman A. Brautigam, a former classmate of hers at Yale University, and they lived in Pennsylvania. She died August 19, 1996 in Bucks County, Pennsylvania.
The papers of Virginia Corwin contain extensive notes from her student days at Yale University including her seminars with H. Richard Niebuhr in Christian ethics and Robert L. Calhoun in the History of Christian doctrines. Also included are transcripts from a conference in the 1930s on the work of Henry Burton Sharman on the life of Christ.
The bulk of the papers consist of her research notes and preliminary drafts for a book on the history of modern Hinduism that was never published. In addition there are some notes on other non-Christian religions.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
History of the Collection
The Virginia Corwin papers were created by Virginia Corwin, Professor of Religion at Smith College from 1930-1966.
Additional Information
Related Material
Researchers should also view:
52. Religion
Bibliography
Corwin, Virginia. St. Ignatius and Christianity in Antioch. (New Haven, Yale University Press, 1960)
Corwin, Virginia. "The Personal Touch: Advice Unlimited," Smith Alumnae Quarterly 29 (May 1938): 246-247.
Bixler, J. S. "Religion in the New Curriculum," Smith Alumnae Quarterly 22 (November 1930): 59-60.
Lincoln, Eleanor T. "Virginia Corwin," Smith Alumnae Quarterly 57 (Summer 1966): 215.
Theological Discussion Group Papers, Yale University Library, Divinity Library Special Collections, Record Group no. 43.
- Series I. General
  - Biographical materials (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, addresses, travel notes 1940s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous items (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II. Research Notes and Writings
  - Sermon - Mark 8:31-37 -- typescript April 12, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Teaching of Religion (chapter in Liberal Learning and Religion) 1951 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Modern Hinduism - notes and outline (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - A Study on Reform in Modern Hinduism - preface - handwritten draft (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Gandhi - handwritten draft (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Gandhi - typescript draft 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Gandhi - notes on (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Understanding Gandhi's Ways, by Stephen Hay 1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Richard V. De Smet pamphlets (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Rammohun Roy - typescript draft - 1st draft (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Rammohun Roy - typescript and handwritten draft - 3rd draft? (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Rammohun Roy - handwritten and typescript draft - additional (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Rammohun Roy - notes on (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Rammohun Roy - articles on (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Ramakrishna - handwritten and typescript draft and notes (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - The Transformation of Sri Ramakrishna, by Walter G. Neevel, Jr. 1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - K. C. Sen - handwritten and typescript draft and notes (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - K. C. Sen - articles on (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Aurobindo - handwritten draft and notes (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Debendranath Tagore - handwritten and typescript drafts (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Debendranath Tagore - articles on (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Tagore - notes on (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Vivekanada - typescript draft (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Vivekanada - handwritten draft and notes (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Modern Hinduism bibliography (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Tukfatul Muwahhiddin - notes on (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Satyagraha - notes on (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Bengali Renaissance notes (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Hinduism in American - notes one (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Man the Mystic: Zen Buddhism and Psychoanalysis, by Virginia Corwin - typescript and handwritten drafts and notes - presentation for Smith College's Alumni College (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Village Celebration in Malabar, by Virginia Corwin - handwritten draft (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Ramakrishna Mission pamphlets 1946-1972 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Arya Samaj - articles on (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Brahma Samaj - article on (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - India - Newspaper clippings, etc. 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Robert Bellah - selections from (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - The Basis for the Hindu Act of Truth, by W. Norman Brown 1940 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - The Myth of the Four Yugas in the Sanskrit Puranas: a Dimensional Study, by Cornelia D. Church 1971 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Letters on Hinduism, by Bankim Chandra Chatterjee 1940 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - J. Krishnamurti: the Pathless Way, by Diana Eck 1968 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Ritual and Cult of Indian Buddhists, by Adelle M. Fiske 1970 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Indian temple architecture - articles by F. H. Gravely and others 1959-1962 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - The Characteristics of Oriental Nothingness, by Shin-ichi Hisamatsu (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Siva, Minaksi and Vishnu: Reflections on a Popular Myth in Madurai, by D. Dennis Hudson (?) (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Sunyata as a Master-Symbol, by Winston L. King (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - One Fire, Three Fires, Five Fires: Vedic Symbols in Transition, by David M. Knipe (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Possession, Dance and Religion in North Malabar, Kerala, India 1964 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Hindu Monastic Orders and the Continuing Process of Syncretism: selected bibliography; by David McGregor Miller 1970 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Ken Morgan on Vivekananda -- notes (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Reaching for the Moon: Exploring Asian Religious Paths, by Kenneth W. Morgan 1990 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Buddhism and the Changing Society in Modern Ceylon, by W. Pachow 1970 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Religion and Political Authority in Modern Burma, by John Pemberton (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Saiva Siddhanta, by S. Pillai (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Hindu Symbolisms in Syro-Malabar Liturgy and Devotions, by Cyriac K. Pullapilly (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - A. K. Saran - articles and syllabi 1960s-1972 (Box 2, Folder 54-55)
  - The Ideal Social Order as Portrayed in the Sinhalese Chronicles, by Bardwell L. Smith (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - An Apology for the Present System of Hindoo Worship, by Mkityanjaya Vidyalankar (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - O. H. de A. Wijesekera - articles 1960s (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Smith College Religion 11 - syllabi 1950s (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Centemporary Hindu Thought - Smith College Religion 36b and 311b - Leela Gole 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Buddhism - Smith College Religion 24b and 36b - Syllabi and notes (Wijesekera?) 1966 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Religion in Modern India - Smith College Religion 370b - Syllabi, lecture notes, etc. - Virginia Corwin and D. Dennis Hudson 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Modern Hinduism - Wells College Religion 326 - Virginia Corwin 1972 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Seminar notes - Christian Ethics - Richard Niebuhr - Yale University 1932-1933 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Seminar notes - World Religions - Yale University 1930s (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Seminar notes - History of Christian Doctrines - Robert L. Calhoun 1932 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Collected poetry and liturgies - scrapbook (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Notes from the Minnesinger Seminar 1932 on Henry Burton Sharman - notes from Esther Duke 1931?, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 68-69)
  - Note cards - notes on general subjects, but primarily note cards on topics to be covered in Corwin's study on modern Hinduism (Box 4)